Chapters 1 through 17 Review and Expansion In the first 17 chapters of the American
Accent Training Program, we covered the concepts that form the basis of American
speech, intonation, word groups, the staircase, and liaisons, or word
connections. We also discussed some key sounds, such as ah, ah, and uh, cat-caught
-cut, the L, the American T, and the American R. Let's briefly review each
item. Intonation. You've learned some of the reasons for changing the pitch or
saying a word louder, or even stretching out some words in a sentence. For
example, new information. He bought a car. Contrast. Timing is more important than
technique. Opinion. It feels like mink but I think it's rabbit. Can't. He can't do
it. You've also learned how to change meaning by shifting intonation without
changing any of the actual words in a sentence. I applied for the job, not you.
I applied for the job, but I don't think I'll get it. I applied for the job, not I
applied myself to the job. I applied for the job, the one I've been dreaming about
for years. I applied for the job, not the lifestyle. Miscellaneous reminders of
intonation. When you have a verb preposition combination, the stress
usually goes on the preposition. Pick up, put down, fall in, and so on. Otherwise,
prepositions are placed in the valleys of your intonation. It's for you. They're
from L.A. When you have initials, the stress goes on the last letter. IBM, P.O.
Box, ASAP, I.O.U., and so on. Liaisons and glides Through liaisons, you learned about
voiced and unvoiced consonants, where they're located in the mouth, and which
sounds are likely to attach to a following one. You are also introduced to glides. 1.
Consonant and vowel. Put it on. 2. Consonant and consonant. Racetrack. 3.
Vowel and vowel. No other. 4. T and Y. Put you on. D and Y. Had you? S and Y, yes you
do. Z and Y, is your cat. Cat, caught, cut. This lesson was an introduction to
pronunciation, especially those highly characteristic sounds, ah, ah, and uh. Ah.
The jaw moves down and back while the back of the tongue pushes forward and the tip
touches the back of the bottom teeth. Sometimes it almost sounds like there's a
Y in there. Ah. Relax the tongue. Open the throat like you're letting the doctor see
all the way to your toes. Ah. Uh. This sound is the sound that would come out if
you were pushed lightly in the stomach. Uh. You don't need to put your mouth in
any particular position at all. The sound is created when the air is forced out of
the diaphragm and past the vocal cords. The American T. T is T, a clear popped
sound when it's at the top of the staircase. At the beginning of a word,
table. In a stressed syllable, intend. In ST, TS, TR, and CT clusters, instruct.
Replaces D after unvoiced consonants, hoped. T is D, a softer sound when it's in
the middle of a staircase, in an unstressed position between vowels,
cattle. T and D are held, not pronounced with a sharp burst of air, when they're at
the bottom of the staircase. At the end of a word, bot, T is held before N,
unstressed and followed by T-E-N or T-A-I-N, Written T is swallowed by N. Interview
The L The L is closely connected with the schwa. Your tongue drops down and back as
if it were going to say uh, but the tip curls up and attaches to the top of the
mouth, which requires a strong movement of the tip of the tongue. The air comes out
around the sides of the tongue, and the sound is held for slightly longer than
you'd think. The American R. The main difference between a consonant and a vowel
is that with a consonant, there is contact at some point in your mouth. It might be
the lips, p, the tongue tip, n, or the throat, g. Like a vowel, however, the R
doesn't touch anywhere. It's similar to a schwa, but your tongue curls back in a
retroflex movement and produces deep in the throat. The tongue doesn't touch the
top of the mouth. Another way to approach it is to put your tongue in position for E
and then slide straight back to ear. Some people are more comfortable collapsing
their tongue back like an accordion instead of curling it. It doesn't make any
difference in the so do whichever you prefer. Application exercises. Now you
need to use the exercises you've learned so far and to make the transference to
your everyday speech. In the beginning, the process is very slow and analytical,
but as you do it over and over again, it becomes natural and unconscious. The
exercises presented here will show you how. For example, take any phrase that may
catch your ear during a conversation it's unfamiliar or for whatever other reason,
and work it through the practice sequence used in Review Exercise 1.